Tim CD Lucas

PERSONAL INFORMATION

email

imcdlucas@gmail.com

github www.github.com/timcdlucas

scholar Google scholar

phone 07415 863 536

PRESENT APPOINTMENT

2020-present Imperial College

Early Career Research Fellow During this fellowship I aim to develop statistical regression methods that properly accounts for human movement and use these methods to estimate the effects of air pollution on disease. Due to the coronavirus pandemic I have also spent a considerable fraction of my time working on models of contact tracing.

PREVIOUS APPOINTMENTS

Jan–June University of Oxford

2020

Senior Post Doc. Models of neglected tropical diseases, contributing to software and promoting

good research software practices such as version control and unit testing.

2016–2020 University of Oxford, Malaria Atlas Project

Post Doc. I worked as a postdoctoral research scientist in geospatial epidemiology with

the Malaria Atlas Project at the University of Oxford. I have made large contributions to the *first high resolution, global, space-time* estimates of both *Plasmodium falciparum* and *P. vivax* leading to two high-profile publications. To this end I have developed new statistical methods that combine *machine learning* and *geostatistics*. I have also supervised research assistants on smaller projects,

leading to one publication.

2018–2019 Shared parental leave

Parental leave Six months shared parental leave.

Jan–July 2016 University College London

Research I enabled the Madingley Model to run on a high performance cluster and

Programmer ported code to R for morphological analyses amongst other tasks.

EDUCATION

2012–2016 University College London, CoMPLEX

PhD The role of population structure and size in determining bat pathogen richness

I used *network epidemiological models* and phylogenetic regression to study the epidemiology of bat-borne diseases with applications to zoonotic surveillance. I

conceived the projects and managed my own budget. [pdf] Supervisors: Prof. Kate Jones & Dr Hilde Herbots

2011–2012 University College London, CoMPLEX

MRes Modelling Biological Complexity · Merit

Projects included adapting 'ideal gas' models to acoustic data, analysing moment closures for a pair-approximation model of plant ecology and applying a partly applying a partly and to a library of bet salls.

novel *machine learning* method to a library of bat calls.

2006–2010 University of Sheffield, Animal & Plant Sciences

MBioSci Zoology · First

For my final project I used *wavelet* analysis to study multi-annual *cycles in malaria* incidence in Thailand.

OTHER PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITES

Peer Review

Journals Reviewed for:

Journal of Theoretical Biology, BMC Infectious Diseases, PLoS Pathogens, Malaria Journal, Methods in Ecology and Evolution, Global Ecology and Biogeography, Ecology and Evolution, Remote Sensing in Ecology and Conservation, ROpenSci, National Academy Science Letters, Journal of Advances in Medicine and Medical Research.

PEER-REVIEWED PUBLICATIONS

2020 **Lucas TCD** (2020) A translucent box: interpretable machine learning in ecology. Ecological Monographs. [pdf]

Lucas TCD, Nandi AK, et al. (2020) *Improving disaggregation models of malaria incidence by ensembling non-linear models of prevalence*. Spatial and Spatiotemporal Epidemiology. [pdf]

Lucas TCD*, Davis E*, et al. (2020) Engagement and adherence trade-offs for *SARS-CoV-2 contact tracing*. In Press. Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B. [pdf]

Lucas TCD, Pollington T, Davis E and Hollingsworth D. (2020) *Responsible modelling: Unit testing for infectious disease epidemiology*. Epidemics. [pdf]

Nguyen M, Howes RE, **Lucas TCD**, et al. (2020) Mapping malaria seasonality in Madagascar using health facility data. BMC medicine, 18(1), 1-11 [pdf]

Rathmes G, Rumisha SF, **Lucas TCD**, et al. (2020) Global estimation of anti-malarial drug effectiveness for the treatment of uncomplicated Plasmodium falciparum malaria 1991–2019. Malaria Journal. [pdf]

Crellen T, Pi L, et al. (2020) *Dynamics of SARS-CoV-2 with Waning Immunity in the UK Population*. In Press. Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B. [pdf]

Toor J, Adams ER, et al. (2020) Predicted impact of COVID-19 on neglected tropical disease programs and the opportunity for innovation. Clinical Infectious Diseases. [pdf]

Graham M, Ayabina D, **Lucas TCD**, et al. (2020) SCHISTOX: An individual based model for the epidemiology and control of schistosomiasis. Infectious Disease Modelling. In Press.

Weiss DJ, **Lucas TCD**, Nguyen M, et al. (2019) *The global landscape of* Plasmodium falciparum *prevalence, incidence, and mortality* 2000–2017. The Lancet 394, 10195, 322–331. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(19)31097-9 [pdf]

Battle KE, **Lucas TCD**, Nguyen M, et al. (2019) Mapping the global endemicity and clinical burden of Plasmodium vivax 2000–2017. The Lancet 394, 10195, 332–343. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(19)31096-7 [pdf]

Zhu SJ, et al. (2019) The origins and relatedness structure of mixed infections vary with local prevalence of P. falciparum malaria. eLife 8 e40845. doi: 10.7554/eLife.40845 [pdf]

Weiss DJ, Nelson A, Gibson HS et al. (2018) A global map of travel time to cities to

2019

2018

assess inequalities in accessibility in 2015. Nature 553 (7688), 333 [pdf]

Pfeffer D, Lucas TCD, May D et al. (2018) malariaAtlas: an R interface to global malariometric data hosted by the Malaria Atlas Project. Malaria Journal 17:352 doi: 10.1186/s12936-018-2500-5 [pdf]

Redding D, Lucas TCD, Blackburn T & Jones KE. (2017) Evaluating Bayesian spatial methods for modelling species distributions models with clumped and restricted data. PLoS One [pdf]

Golding N, August TA, **Lucas TCD**, Gavaghan DJ, van Loon EE & McInerny G. (2017) *The zoon R package for reproducible and shareable species distribution modelling*. Methods in Ecology and Evolution. doi: 10.1111/2041-210X.12858 [pdf]

- 2015 **Lucas TCD***, Moorcroft EA*, Freeman R, Rowcliffe MJ & Jones KE. (2015) *A* generalised random encounter model for estimating animal density with remote sensor data. Methods in Ecology and Evolution. doi: 10.1111/2041-210X.12346 [pdf]
- Walters CL, Collen A, **Lucas TCD**, Mroz K, Sayer CA and Jones KE. (2013)
 Challenges of Using Bioacoustics to Globally Monitor Bats. in *Bat Evolution*, *Ecology, and Conservation*. Springer New York. 479-499.
- GBD For Global Burden of Disease capstone papers please see end of document.
 - * Co-first authors.

PEER-REVIEWED CONFERENCE PROCEEDINGS

Law HC, Sejdinovic D, et al. (2018) Variational learning on aggregate outputs with Gaussian processes. Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems [pdf]

GRANTS AWARDED

2020 · MRC Centre Early Career Research Fellowships. Three years wages and expenses. £300,000

2020 · Co-investigator on multi-centre grant. *An analytical framework for Test, Trace and Isolate in the UK: optimising and targeting deployment alongside other measures* UKRI-DHSC COVID-19 Rapid Response Rolling Call. Grant COV0659. £412,720

TEACHING AND SUPERVISION

- 2020 · Organised and delivered four hour workshop (twice due to demand). "Machine Learning in the Health Sciences". Two hours practical workshop and two hours of case studies from members of the department.
- 2020 $\,\cdot\,$ Internal workshops on unit testing, cluster computing and mixed-effects models.
- 2019 $\,\cdot\,$ Co-wrote and ran an afternoon workshop. "Advanced Statistical Modelling with TMB".
- 2019 · Thesis committee for PhD student Dan Pfeffer.
- 2018 · Supervised two research assistants on side projects resulting in one publication (pdf).
- 2017 \cdot Wrote and gave a two day workshop 'Geospatial statistics with R and INLA' at UiTM, Malaysia.
- $2015\,\cdot\,$ Demonstrator for reproducible species distribution modelling workshop run by Quantitative Ecology special interest group at BES.
- 2013–2014 · Online tutor for SysMIC, a course for teaching quantitative skills to biologists. Answering questions online and marking assessments.

INVITED TALKS

Model stacking to incorporate auxiliary data for malaria mapping. 2020

Talk at workshop on: Machine Learning in Behaviour, Ecology and Evolution,

University of Neuchâtel, Switzerland

Predicting malaria risk from diverse and multilevel data. 2017

Plenary at SDCS2017, Springer

COMPUTATIONAL SKILLS AND SOFTEWARE

Statistical methods

Geospatial statistics, machine learning, Bayesian inference, TMB, Stan.

Languages

R (expert level), Python, Matlab, Mathematica, SQL.

Other

Experience in R package development, Git/Github, unit testing, continuous integration, shell/ssh and high performance computing.

Software

Nandi A, Lucas TCD, Arambepola A, Python A. disaggregation: Disaggregation Modelling. https://github.com/aknandi/disaggregation

Pfeffer D, Lucas TCD, May D, Keddie S, Rozier J, Gibson H. malaria Atlas: An R Interface to Open-Access Malaria Data, Hosted by the 'Malaria Atlas Project'. www.github.com/malaria-atlas-project/malariaAtlas

Lucas TCD, Python A, Redding D. *INLAutils: Utility Functions for 'INLA'*. www.github.com/timcdlucas/INLAutils

Lucas TCD, Goswami A. paleomorph: Geometric Morphometric Tools for Paleobiology. www.github.com/timcdlucas/paleomorph

August T, Lucas TCD, Golding N, van Loon E, McInerny G. Zoon: Reproducible, Accessible & Shareable Species Distribution Modelling. www.github.com/zoonproject/zoon

Lucas TCD. palettetown: Use Pokemon Inspired Colour Palettes www.github.com/timcdlucas/palettetown

REFEREES

Dr Frédéric Piel Prof. Peter Gething School of Public Health Professor of Epidemiology Imperial College Big Data Institute Praed Street University of Oxford St Mary's Campus London Oxford United Kingdom United Kingdom

WC1E 6BT OX₃ 7LF

Email: f.piel@imperial.ac.uk Email: Peter.Gething@telethonkids.org.au

Tel: +44 (o)20 7594 3346

GLOBAL BURDEN OF DISEASE PUBLICATIONS

2020

GBD 2019 Diseases and Injuries Collaborators (2020) Global burden of 369 diseases and injuries in 204 countries and territories, 1990–2019: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2019. The Lancet, 396 [pdf]

GBD 2017 Disease and Injury Incidence and Prevalence Collaborators (2018) Global burden of 369 diseases and injuries in 204 countries and territories, 1990–2019: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2019 The Lancet, 392 [pdf]

2018 GBD 2017 Risk Factor Collaborators (2018) Global, regional, and national comparative risk assessment of 84 behavioural, environmental and occupational, and metabolic risks or clusters of risks for 195 countries and territories, 1990–2017: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2017. The Lancet, 392 [pdf]

GBD 2017 Disease and Injury Incidence and Prevalence Collaborators (2018) Global, regional, and national incidence, prevalence, and years lived with disability for 354 diseases and injuries for 195 countries and territories, 1990–2017: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2017. The Lancet, 392 [pdf]

GBD 2017 DALYs and HALE Collaborators (2018) Global, regional, and national disability-adjusted life-years (DALYs) for 359 diseases and injuries and healthy life expectancy (HALE) for 195 countries and territories, 1990–2017: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2017. The Lancet, 392 [pdf]

GBD 2017 Mortality Collaborators (2018) *Global, regional, and national age-sex-specific mortality and life expectancy,* 1950–2017: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2017. The Lancet, 392 [pdf]

GBD 2016 Healthcare Access and Quality Collaborators (2017) Measuring performance on the Healthcare Access and Quality Index for 195 countries and territories and selected subnational locations: a systematic analysis from the Global Burden of Disease Study 2016. The Lancet, 391 (10136) [pdf]

GBD 2016 Disease and Injury Incidence and Prevalence Collaborators (2017) Global, regional, and national incidence, prevalence, and years lived with disability for 328 diseases and injuries for 195 countries, 1990–2016: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2016. The Lancet, 390 [pdf]

GBD 2016 Causes of Death Collaborators (2017) *Global, regional, and national age-sex specific mortality for 264 causes of death, 1980–2016: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2016.* The Lancet, 390 [pdf]

GBD 2016 DALYs and HALE Collaborators (2017) Global, regional, and national disability-adjusted life-years (DALYs) for 333 diseases and injuries and healthy life expectancy (HALE) for 195 countries and territories, 1990–2016: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2016. The Lancet, 390[pdf]

GBD 2016 SDG Collaborators (2017) Measuring progress and projecting attainment on the basis of past trends of the health-related Sustainable Development Goals in 188 countries: an analysis from the Global Burden of Disease Study 2016. The Lancet, 390 [pdf]

16th February, 2021

2017